foreign
experience differs between individual
and group health insurance plans
individual health insurance policies can
come with several complexities and
challenges that causes stress for
policyholders during the clean process
but group policies tend to have less
complexities and confusion last week a
friend's father asked for help with his
individual health insurance claim they
needed to have a need placement surgery
and the insurance completely paid third
party administrator wanted to see copies
of his policies from when he first got
it but he did not have a report from
more than a year ago and hence was
having trouble
this is a common problem for people with
individual health insurance policies
they often have to go back and forth
with insurance companies when trying to
settle a claim for people who are a part
of group policies doesn't face these
kind of problems this is because of
several reasons
foreign
policies is waiting periods individual
policies have different types of waiting
periods the first is an initial waiting
period which can last from 30 to 90 days
and can
then there is disease specific waiting
period where certain named illnesses
cannot be covered until the waiting
period is over this can last from one
year to four years
common illnesses on this list include
hernia knee replacement cataract
lastly there is a waiting period for
pre-existing
existing lasts from two years to four
years
if for a condition like high blood
pressure has been you know diagnosed
before the policy was issued then the
related claims such as a heart attack
claim can only be covered after the
permitting period is over
at the time of claim the insurance
company checks if it is subject to any
of these waiting periods
in almost all the group policies these
waiting periods are waived another issue
that arises with individual policy is
that of policy supplements while the
policy supplements may be present in
individual
and remote the policies but the way they
are applying is different in case of
individual policies uh the Caps are
usually linked to the sun is short for
example room rent cap may be stated as
one percent of the sum is short it is
important to determine what the
applicable summer short is
the reasons for delays in plane
processing poor claim experience
some individual policies consider
accumulated no gain bonus as part of the
summation it is important to check if
the sub shot was increased in recent
years and if the incremental sum is
short is subject to any waiting period
these these issues do not arise in case
of group policies in group policies
there is no such accumulative nuclein
bonus and the semi short is defined for
each year at the policy start date
even if there was an enhancement in
previous years then also the Caps would
be linked to the current year some shop
another factor that leads to back and
forth communication is the various
add-ons that can be included in
individual policies these add-ons may be
unique to a specific insurer and not
commonly chosening as a result TPA that
handles the claim May Fail sometimes to
check for them the initial Claims
Settlement may be processed as usual
however once it is brought through the
notice of insurance company that add-on
was chosen then they may correct it in
group policies generally the conditions
are saying for a group of a particular
group of members and there is less
chance of confusion
fail to disclose pre-existing condition
your claim could be rejected when an
individual policyholder files a claim
the insurer will check if there was any
non-disclosure at the time of policy
application this can be a major issue
this scrutiny can feel like an attempt
to deny the claim for policy holder the
insurer will investigate or record and
look for potential levels in case of
group policies there is no underwriting
of individual members hence there is
guaranteed coverage and so such checks
are not applicable for good policies
in conclusion to navigate the
complexities of individual policies and
ensure smooth claim process the
policyholders should be familiar with
the policy terms and conditions be
proactive in addressing the issues that
may arise and engage with the insurance
broker who can help them navigate the
insurance ecosystem
[Music]